To understand the business of mythology
لكي نفهم قطاع الأعمال وتأثره بالأساطير
and what a Chief Belief Officer is supposed to do,
وما الذي يجب على مدير عام الإيمانيات عمله
you have to hear a story
يجب علينا ان نسمع قصة
of Ganesha,
عن جانيشا
the elephant-headed god
الإله ذو رأس الفيل
who is the scribe of storytellers,
كاتب رواة القصص
and his brother,
وأخيه
the athletic warlord of the gods,
إله الحرب الرياضي
Kartikeya.
كارتيكيا
The two brothers one day decided to go on a race,
في يوم من الأيام قرر الأخوان ان يخوضا سباقا
three times around the world.
ثلاث مرات حول العالم
Kartikeya leapt on his peacock
كارتيكيا قفز على طاووسه
and flew around the continents
وطار حول القارات
and the mountains and the oceans.
والجبال والمحيطات
He went around once,
دار حولهم مرة
he went around twice,
دار حولهم مرتين
he went around thrice.
دار حولهم ثلاث
But his brother, Ganesha,
ولكن أخيه، جانيشا
simply walked around his parents
ببساطة دار حول أبويه
once, twice, thrice,
مرة، مرتين، ثلاث مرات
and said, "I won."
وقال: لقد فزت
"How come?" said Kartikeya.
قال كارتيكيا: كيف ذاك؟
And Ganesha said,
فقال جانيشا
"You went around 'the world.'
أنت درت حول العالم
I went around 'my world.'"
اما انا فدرت حول عالمي
What matters more?
أيهما يهم أكثر؟
If you understand the difference between 'the world' and 'my world,'
إذا فهمت الفرق بين العالم وعالمي
you understand the difference between logos and mythos.
ستفهم الفرق بين الرؤية العقلية والخيالية للعالم
'The world' is objective,
العالم" موضوعي"
logical, universal, factual,
منطقي، عالمي، واقعي
scientific.
علمي
'My world' is subjective.
عالمي" ذاتي"
It's emotional. It's personal.
عاطفي، شخصي
It's perceptions, thoughts, feelings, dreams.
أنه إدراك، أفكار، مشاعر، أحلام
It is the belief system that we carry.
إنه النظام الإيماني الذي نحمله
It's the myth that we live in.
إنه الاسطورة التي نعيش فيها
'The world' tells us how the world functions,
العالم" يخبرنا كيف يعمل العالم"
how the sun rises,
كيف تشرق الشمس
how we are born.
كيف نولد
'My world' tells us why the sun rises,
عالمي" يخبرنا لماذا تشرق الشمس"
why we were born.
لماذا نولد
Every culture is trying to understand itself:
كل ثقافة تحاول ان تفهم نفسها
"Why do we exist?"
لماذا نحن موجودون؟
And every culture comes up with its own understanding of life,
وكل ثقافة تأتي بمفهمومها الخاص للحياة
its own customized version of mythology.
نسختها الخاصة بها من الأساطير
Culture is a reaction to nature,
الثقافة هي نتاج تفاعل مع الطبيعة
and this understanding of our ancestors
وما فهمه أسلافنا
is transmitted generation from generation
تنتقل من جيل إلى جيل
in the form of stories, symbols and rituals,
في شكل قصص، ورموز، وطقوس
which are always indifferent to rationality.
وكلها لا تبالي بالمنطق
And so, when you study it, you realize
وأنت عندما تدرسها، تبدأ تدرك
that different people of the world
ان الناس حول العالم
have a different understanding of the world.
لديهم فهم مختلف له
Different people see things differently --
ناس مختلفون يرون الأشياء مختلفة
different viewpoints.
وجهات نظر مختلفة
There is my world and there is your world,
هناك عالمي، وهناك عالمك
and my world is always better than your world,
وعالمي دائما أحسن من عالمك
because my world, you see, is rational
لأن عالمي، كما ترى، عقلاني
and yours is superstition.
وعالمك خرافة
Yours is faith.
عالمك مجرد عقائد
Yours is illogical.
عالمك غير منطقي
This is the root of the clash of civilizations.
هذه هي جذور صراع الحضارات
It took place, once, in 326 B.C.
لقد حدثت، مرة، سنة 326 قبل الميلاد
on the banks of a river called the Indus,
على ضفاف نهر يسمى السند
now in Pakistan.
يوجد الان في باكستان
This river lends itself to India's name.
أخذ النهر إسمه من إسم الهند
India. Indus.
الهند، السند
Alexander, a young Macedonian,
الإسكندر، مقدوني شاب
met there what he called a "gymnosophist,"
"قابل هناك من سماه بـ "جيمنوسوفست
which means "the naked, wise man."
وتعني الرجل العاري، الحكيم
We don't know who he was.
لا نعرف من هو
Perhaps he was a Jain monk,
ربما كان راهب من الديانة الجاينية
like Bahubali over here,
كما "باهوبلي"، هنا
the Gomateshwara Bahubali
الراهب الأكبر باهوبلي
whose image is not far from Mysore.
والذي لا تبعد صورته هذه عن مدينة مايسور
Or perhaps he was just a yogi
أو ربما كان مجرد يوغاني
who was sitting on a rock, staring at the sky
كان يجلس على صخرة، يحدق في النجوم
and the sun and the moon.
والشمس، والقمر
Alexander asked, "What are you doing?"
!فقال الأسكندر: ماذا تفعل؟
and the gymnosophist answered,
أجاب الراهب
"I'm experiencing nothingness."
أنا أختبر اللاشيء
Then the gymnosophist asked,
وسأله الراهب
"What are you doing?"
!انت، ماذا تفعل؟
and Alexander said, "I am conquering the world."
فأجاب الإسكندر: أنا أغزو العالم
And they both laughed.
وضحك كلاهما
Each one thought that the other was a fool.
كل منهما أعتقد ان الأخر مغفل
The gymnosophist said, "Why is he conquering the world?
قال الراهب: لم يغزو العالم؟
It's pointless."
انه أمر تافه
And Alexander thought,
وفكر الإسكندر
"Why is he sitting around, doing nothing?
لماذا يجلس هكذا، لا يفعل شيئا؟
What a waste of a life."
يالها من مضيعة للحياة
To understand this difference in viewpoints,
لكي نفهم هذا الإختلاف في وجهات النظر
we have to understand
يجب علينا أن نفهم
the subjective truth of Alexander --
الحقيقة الشخصية للإسكندر
his myth, and the mythology that constructed it.
أسطورته، والأساطير التي بنتها
Alexander's mother, his parents, his teacher Aristotle
والدة الإسكندر، والديه، معلمه أرسطو
told him the story of Homer's "Iliad."
حكوا له قصة "الإلياذه" لهوميروس
They told him of a great hero called Achilles,
أخبروه عن بطل عظيم يدعى أخيل
who, when he participated in battle, victory was assured,
أنه عندما يشارك في معركة، فأن النصر محتوم
but when he withdrew from the battle,
ولكنه عندما ينسحب من المعركة
defeat was inevitable.
فإن الهزيمة لا مفر منها
"Achilles was a man who could shape history,
أخيل كان رجلا يستطيع نحت التاريخ
a man of destiny,
رجل أقدار
and this is what you should be, Alexander."
وهذا ما يجب أن تكون عليه يا أسكندر
That's what he heard.
هذا ما سمعه
"What should you not be?
ما الذي يجب ألا تكونه؟
You should not be Sisyphus,
يجب عليك الا تكون سيزيف
who rolls a rock up a mountain all day
الذي كان يدحرج الصخرة لأعلى الجبل كل يوم
only to find the boulder rolled down at night.
فقط ليجد انها قد تدحرجت لأسفل في الليل
Don't live a life which is monotonous,
لا تعش حياه رتيبة (مملة)
mediocre, meaningless.
عادية، لا معنى لها
Be spectacular! --
كن مذهلا
like the Greek heroes,
كأبطال الأغريق
like Jason, who went across the sea
كجاسون، الذي عبر البحر
with the Argonauts and fetched the Golden Fleece.
برفقة الأرجون ليجلب الصوف الذهبي
Be spectacular like Theseus,
كن مذهلا كزيسيوس
who entered the labyrinth and killed the bull-headed Minotaur.
الذي دخل المتاهة وقتل المينوتور ذو رأس الثور
When you play in a race, win! --
!عندما تشارك في سباق، فز
because when you win, the exhilaration of victory
لأنك عندما تفز، فأن تهليلات النصر
is the closest you will come to the ambrosia of the gods."
هي أقرب ما ستذوق من طعام الآلهة
Because, you see, the Greeks believed
لأنه ،كما ترون، فإن الإغريق يؤمنون
you live only once,
أنك تعيش مرة واحدة فقط
and when you die, you have to cross the River Styx.
وعندما تموت، يجب عليك ان تعبر نهر ستيكس
And if you have lived an extraordinary life,
ولو أنك عشت حياة مميزة
you will be welcomed to Elysium,
سيرحب بك في الإليزيم
or what the French call "Champs-Élysées" --
"أو ما يسميه الفرنسيون "الشانزليزيه
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
the heaven of the heroes.
جنة الأبطال
But these are not the stories that the gymnosophist heard.
ولكن هذه ليست القصص التي سمعها الراهب
He heard a very different story.
لقد سمع قصة مختلفة تماما
He heard of a man called Bharat,
سمع عن رجل يدعى بهارت
after whom India is called Bhārata.
والتي سميت الهند على أسمه، بهاراتا
Bharat also conquered the world.
بهارت أيضا غزا العالم
And then he went to the top-most peak
ثم ذهب الى أعلى قمة
of the greatest mountain of the center of the world
في أعلى جبل في مركز العالم
called Meru.
يدعى ميرو
And he wanted to hoist his flag to say,
أراد ان يغرز علمه ليقول
"I was here first."
أنا كنت هنا أولا
But when he reached the mountain peak,
ولكنه عندما بلغ قمة الجبل
he found the peak covered with countless flags
وجدها مغطاة بأعلام لا تحصى
of world-conquerors before him,
لغزاة عالم من قبله
each one claiming "'I was here first' ...
كل منهم ادعى: انا كنت هنا أولا
that's what I thought until I came here."
هذا ما كنت أعتقد قبل أن آتي هنا
And suddenly, in this canvas of infinity,
وفجأة، في هذا الخضم من اللانهائية
Bharat felt insignificant.
شعر بهارت بالضألة
This was the mythology of the gymnosophist.
هذه كانت أساطير الراهب
You see, he had heroes, like Ram -- Raghupati Ram
كما ترون، كان لديه أبطال، مثل رام - راجوبتي رام
and Krishna, Govinda Hari.
وكريشنا، غوفيندا هاري
But they were not two characters on two different adventures.
ولكنهما لم يكونا مجرد شخصين في مغامرمتين مختلفتين
They were two lifetimes of the same hero.
كانا دورتي حياة لنفس البطل
When the Ramayana ends the Mahabharata begins.
عندما ينتهي راميانا، يبدأ ماهبهارات
When Ram dies, Krishna is born.
عندما يموت رام، يولد كريشنا
When Krishna dies, eventually he will be back as Ram.
عندما يموت كريشنا، في النهاية فأنه سيعود كرام
You see, the Indians also had a river
كما ترون، للهنود أيضا نهر
that separates the land of the living from the land of the dead.
يفصل ما بين أرض الآحياء وأرض الموتى
But you don't cross it once.
ولكنك لا تعبره مرة واحدة
You go to and fro endlessly.
ولكنك تذهب وتجيء بلا نهاية
It was called the Vaitarani.
سمي بنهر الفايترني
You go again and again and again.
انت تذهب مرة أخرى وأخرى وأخرى
Because, you see,
لانه كما ترون
nothing lasts forever in India, not even death.
لا شيء يدوم للابد في الهند، ولا حتى الموت
And so, you have these grand rituals
ولذلك فأنه لدينا هذه الطقوس العظيمة
where great images of mother goddesses are built
حيث تبنى صور عظيمة للإلهة الأم
and worshiped for 10 days ...
وتعبد لعشرة أيام
And what do you do at the end of 10 days?
وماذا نفعل في أخر العشرة أيام؟
You dunk it in the river.
نغمرها في النهر
Because it has to end.
لانه يجب أن تنتهي
And next year, she will come back.
والعام القادم، سوف تعود
What goes around always comes around,
ما يذهب يجب ان يعود
and this rule applies not just to man,
وهذه القاعدة لا تنطبق فقط على الإنسان
but also the gods.
ولكن الآلهه ايضا
You see, the gods
فكما ترون، الآلهه
have to come back again and again and again
لابد ان تعود مره أخرى، وأخرى، وأخرى
as Ram, as Krishna.
كرام، او ككريشنا
Not only do they live infinite lives,
ليس فقط انهم يعيشون حياة خالدة
but the same life is lived infinite times
ولكن نفس الحياة تعاش لمرات لانهائيه
till you get to the point of it all.
حتى تصل لفهم كل الأشياء
"Groundhog Day."
يوم جرذ الأرض - فيلم أمريكي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Two different mythologies.
أسطورتان مختلفتان
Which is right?
ايهما الصواب؟
Two different mythologies, two different ways of looking at the world.
أسطورتان مختلفتان، طريقتان مختلفتان لرؤية العالم
One linear, one cyclical.
واحدة خطية، والأخرى دائرية
One believes this is the one and only life.
احداهما تؤمن ان هذه هي حياتنا الواحدة والوحيدة
The other believes this is one of many lives.
والأخرى تؤمن ان حياتنا واحدة من حيوات عديدة
And so, the denominator of Alexander's life was one.
وبالتالي كان القاسم في حياة الإسكندر هو الواحد
So, the value of his life was the sum total
إذا، كانت قيمة حياته هو مجموع
of his achievements.
إنجازاته
The denominator of the gymnosophist's life was infinity.
القاسم في حياة الراهب كان اللانهايه
So, no matter what he did,
وبالتالي فأنه مهما فعل
it was always zero.
فالنتيجة دائما صفر
And I believe it is this mythological paradigm
وأنا أومن ان هذا المثال الأسطوري
that inspired Indian mathematicians
هو من ألهم الرياضيين الهنود
to discover the number zero.
لإكتشاف الرقم صفر
Who knows?
من يدري؟
And that brings us to the mythology of business.
وهذا يعود بنا الى قطاع الأعمال وعلاقته بالأساطير
If Alexander's belief influenced his behavior,
إذا كان إيمان الإسكندر قد أثر في سلوكه
if the gymnosophist's belief influences his behavior,
إذا كان إيمان الراهب قد أثر في سلوكه
then it was bound to influence the business they were in.
عندها فإن سلوكهم قد أثر في ما كانوا يفعلونه
You see, what is business
كما ترون، فقطاع الأعمال ما هو
but the result of how the market behaves
الا نتيجه لسلوك السوق
and how the organization behaves?
وكيف تتصرف المؤسسات؟
And if you look at cultures around the world,
وإذا نظرت للثقافات حول العالم
all you have to do is understand the mythology
كل ما عليك فعله هو فهم خلفيتهم الأسطوريه
and you will see how they behave and how they do business.
وستفهم كيف يتصرفون، وكيف يقومون بالأعمال
Take a look.
لنأخذ نظرة
If you live only once, in one-life cultures around the world,
اذا عشت لمرة واحدة، في ثقافات الحياة الواحدة
you will see an obsession with binary logic,
ستجد هوس بالمنطق الثنائي
absolute truth, standardization,
حقائق مطلقة، معايرة
absoluteness, linear patterns in design.
مطلق، أنماط تصميم خطيه
But if you look at cultures which have cyclical
ولكن إذا نظرت للثقافات دائرية الحياة
and based on infinite lives, you will see a comfort with fuzzy logic,
التي تبنى على حيوات خالدة، سترى منطق مريح وغير واضح
with opinion,
مع وجهة نظر
with contextual thinking,
تفكير قصصي
with everything is relative, sort of --
كل شيء نسبي، نوعا ما
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
mostly.
غالبا
You look at art. Look at the ballerina,
أنظر الى الفن، انظر الى راقصة الباليه
how linear she is in her performance.
كيف هو خطي آدائها
And then look at the Indian classical dancer,
وانظر للراقص الهندي التقليدي
the Kuchipudi dancer, the Bharatanatyam dancer,
راقص الكوشيبدي، راقص الباهاراتانتايم
curvaceous.
رشيق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then look at business.
ثم أنظر الى قطاع الأعمال
Standard business model:
النموذج المؤسسي التقليدي
vision, mission, values, processes.
رؤية، مهمة، قيم، عمليات
Sounds very much like the journey through
تشبه كثيرا الرحله عبر
the wilderness to the promised land,
البرية لأرض الميعاد
with the commandments held by the leader.
بالوصايا التي نص عليها القائد
And if you comply, you will go to heaven.
إذا أطعت، فستدخل الجنة
But in India there is no "the" promised land.
ولكن في الهند لا يوجد أرض الميعاد
There are many promised lands,
ولكن أراضي ميعاد كثيرة
depending on your station in society,
أعتمادا على مركزك في المجتمع
depending on your stage of life.
أعتمادا على أي مرحلة في حياتك أنت
You see, businesses are not run as institutions,
كما ترون، الأعمال لا تدار كمؤسسات
by the idiosyncrasies of individuals.
ولكن بخصوصيات الأفراد
It's always about taste.
الأمر يتعلق دائما بالذوق
It's always about my taste.
الأمر يتعلق دائما بذوقي
You see, Indian music, for example,
كما ترون، الموسيقى الهندية، كمثال
does not have the concept of harmony.
لا تحتوى على مبدأ التناغم
There is no orchestra conductor.
لا قائد أوركسترا
There is one performer standing there, and everybody follows.
فقط مؤدي واحد، والكل يتبعه
And you can never replicate that performance twice.
ولا يمكنك تكرار الأداء مرتين
It is not about documentation and contract.
الأمر ليس مجرد توثيق، وعقد
It's about conversation and faith.
بل هو تحاور، وإيمان
It's not about compliance. It's about setting,
لا يتعلق الأمر بالطاعة، ,ولكن بالإعداد الجيد والضبط
getting the job done, by bending or breaking the rules --
تنفيذ المهمة، ولو بلوي أو كسر القوانين
just look at your Indian people around here,
أنظروا للهنود الموجودين هنا
you'll see them smile; they know what it is.
سترونهم يبتسمون، أنهم يعلمون ما أتحدث عنه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then look at people who have done business in India,
وأنظروا للناس التي قامت بأعمال في الهند
you'll see the exasperation on their faces.
سترون الغضب على وجوههم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You see, this is what India is today. The ground reality
كما ترون، هذه هي الهند اليوم. الواقع الحي
is based on a cyclical world view.
مبني على النظرة الدائرية للعالم
So, it's rapidly changing, highly diverse,
وبالتالي فهي سريعة التغيير، متنوعة للغاية
chaotic, ambiguous, unpredictable.
فوضوية، غامضة، غير متوقعة
And people are okay with it.
والناس مرتاحة مع هذا الوضع
And then globalization is taking place.
والعولمة قادمة
The demands of modern institutional thinking is coming in.
متطلبات التفكير المؤسسي الحديث قادمة
Which is rooted in one-life culture.
وهي متجذرة من ثقافة الحياة الواحدة
And a clash is going to take place,
والتصادم سيحدث
like on the banks of the Indus.
كما حدث عند ضفاف نهر السند
It is bound to happen.
مقدر لذلك أن يحدث
I have personally experienced it. I'm trained as a medical doctor.
لقد عشت ذلك بنفسي. لقد تدربت كطبيب سريري
I did not want to study surgery. Don't ask me why.
لم أرد ان امارس الجراحة، لا تسألوني لماذا
I love mythology too much.
أحب علم الأساطير جدا
I wanted to learn mythology. But there is nowhere you can study.
أردت ان اتعلمه. ولكن لم يكن يوجد مكان يمكنك دراسته هناك
So, I had to teach it to myself.
ولذا، كان علي أن أعلم نفسي
And mythology does not pay, well, until now.
ولم يأتي علم الاساطير بمنفعة، حسنا، حتى الآن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, I had to take up a job. And I worked in the pharma industry.
ولذا كان علي أن أقبل أي وظيفة. فعملت في صناعة الدواء
And I worked in the healthcare industry.
وعملت في مجال الرعاية الصحية
And I worked as a marketing guy, and a sales guy,
وعملت كرجل تسويق، وكرجل مبيعات
and a knowledge guy, and a content guy, and a training guy.
وكرجل معرفة، وفي ادارة المحتوى، وفي التدريب
I even was a business consultant, doing strategies and tactics.
عملت حتى كمستشار أعمال، أخطط للأسترتيجيات والخطط
And I would see the exasperation
ولقد رأيت السخط والغضب
between my American and European colleagues,
بين زملائي الأمريكيين، والأوروبيين
when they were dealing with India.
عندما يتعاملون مع الهند
Example: Please tell us the process
مثال: من فضلك أخبرنا عن العملية
to invoice hospitals.
التي يجب القيام بها لفوترة المستشفيات
Step A. Step B. Step C. Mostly.
خطوه أ، خطوه ب، خطوه ج. غالبا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
How do you parameterize "mostly"?
كيف تقيس "غالبا"؟
How do you put it in a nice little software? You can't.
كيف تضعها في برنامج صغير لطيف؟ لا يمكن
I would give my viewpoints to people.
أردت ان أشرح للناس وجهة نظري
But nobody was interested in listening to it,
ولكن لم يهتم أحد بالاستماع إليها
you see, until I met Kishore Biyani of the Future group.
حتى قابلت "كيشور بياني" من مجموعة فيوتشر
You see, he has established the largest retail chain, called Big Bazaar.
كان قد أنشأ أكبر سلسلة بيع بالتجزئة، تدعى بيج بازار
And there are more than 200 formats,
وكان هناك أكثر من 200 فرع
across 50 cities and towns of India.
في 50 مدينة في الهند
And he was dealing with diverse and dynamic markets.
وكان يتعامل مع أسواق مختلفة ومتغيرة
And he knew very intuitively,
وهو يعرف عن يقين
that best practices,
ان أفضل الممارسات
developed in Japan and China and Europe and America
التي تم تطويرها في اليابان والصين وأوروبا وأمريكا
will not work in India.
لن تعمل في الهند
He knew that institutional thinking doesn't work in India. Individual thinking does.
كان يعلم أن التفكير المؤسسي لا يعمل في الهند، بل التفكير الفردي
He had an intuitive understanding of the mythic structure of India.
كان لديه فهم بديهي للتركيب الأسطوري للهند
So, he had asked me to be the Chief Belief Officer, and said,
لذا، فقد عينني كمدير الإيمانيات العام، وقال
"All I want to do is align belief."
كل ما أريدك فعله هو تنظيم إيمانات الموظفين
Sounds so simple.
يبدو الأمر بسيطا
But belief is not measurable.
ولكن الإيمان لا يمكن قياسه
You can't measure it. You can't manage it.
لا يمكنك قياسه، لا يمكنك إدارته
So, how do you construct belief?
كيف يممكننا إذا بناء إيمان؟
How do you enhance the sensitivity of people to Indian-ness.
كيف يمكن تحسين فهم الناس لتلك الظاهرة الهندية
Even if you are Indian, it is not very explicit, it is not very obvious.
حتى لو كنت هنديا، فالأمر ليس بهذه الصراحة، ليس بهذا الوضوح
So, I tried to work on the standard model of culture,
لذا فقد ارتأيت ان أجرب النموذج العام لتكوين الثقافات
which is, develop stories, symbols and rituals.
الا وهو القصص الشعبية، الرموز، الطقوس
And I will share one of the rituals with you.
وسأشارككم واحدة من هذه الطقوس
You see it is based on the Hindu ritual of Darshan.
وهي كما ترون مستمدة من الطقس الهندي الدارشان
Hindus don't have the concept of commandments.
الهندوس ليس لديهم مبدأ الوصايا
So, there is nothing right or wrong in what you do in life.
وبالتالي ليس هناك صح أو خطأ فيما يفعلونه في حياتهم
So, you're not really sure how you stand in front of God.
ولذا، فأنهم لا يعرفون كيف ينظر الله إليهم
So, when you go to the temple, all you seek is an audience with God.
ولذا، فأنك عندما تذهب للمعبد، فأن كل ما تريده هو مجرد وجودك مع الإله
You want to see God.
انت تريد ان ترى الإله
And you want God to see you, and hence the gods have very large eyes,
وتريد للإله أن يراك، وبما أن الآلهة تملك عيون كبيرة جدا
large unblinking eyes,
عيون كبيرة لا تطرف
sometimes made of silver,
أحيانا تصنع من الفضة
so they look at you.
وبالتالي فهم ينظرون إليك
Because you don't know whether you're right or wrong, and so all you seek
ولأنك لا تعرف ما إذا كنت على صواب أو خطأ، فأن كل ما ترجوه
is divine empathy.
هو العطف الإلهي
"Just know where I came from, why I did the Jugaad."
فقط أعرف من اين أتيت، لماذا خالفت القوانين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Why did I do the setting,
لماذا قمت بـ"بتهيئة" الأمور
why I don't care for the processes. Just understand me, please."
لماذا لم أهتم بسير العمل، فقط أفهمني، من فضلك
And based on this, we created a ritual for leaders.
وبناءا على هذا، قمنا بخلق طقس خاص للموظفين
After a leader completes his training and is about to take over the store,
بعدما ينهي الموظف تدريبه، وسيبدأ في إستلام متجره
we blindfold him, we surround him with the stakeholders,
فإننا نعصب عينيه، ونحيطه بملاك الأسهم
the customer, his family, his team, his boss.
الزبائن، عائلته، فريق عمله، مديره
You read out his KRA, his KPI, you give him the keys,
نستقرأ مناطق تفاعله، المناطق التي يمكن ان ينتج فيها، وتعطيه مفاتيح هذه المناطق
and then you remove the blindfold.
ثم تزيح عصابة العينين
And invariably, you see a tear,
وبثبات، ترى دمعة
because the penny has dropped.
لأن التأثير قد حدث
He realizes that to succeed,
لقد أدرك، انه لكي ينجح
he does not have to be a "professional,"
لا يجب عليه ان يكون متخصصا
he does not have to cut out his emotions,
لا يجب عليه ان يلغي مشاعره
he has to include all these people
بل يجب عليه ان يضم كل هؤلاء الناس
in his world to succeed, to make them happy,
لعالمه كي ينجح، لكي يسعدهم
to make the boss happy, to make everyone happy.
ليسعد مديره، ليسعد الجميع
The customer is happy, because the customer is God.
ليجعل الزبون سعيد، لأن الزبون هو الإله
That sensitivity is what we need. Once this belief enters,
هذا التفهم هو ما نحتاجه، بمجرد ان يتخلل هذا الإيمان للداخل
behavior will happen, business will happen.
سيظهر السلوك، ستبدا حركة العمل في الظهور
And it has.
وهذا ما حدث
So, then we come back to Alexander
ولذا، حين نعود للإسكندر
and to the gymnosophist.
وللراهب
And everybody asks me, "Which is the better way, this way or that way?"
ويسألني الجميع:" إيهما أفضل، هذا الطريق أم ذاك؟"
And it's a very dangerous question,
وهذا سؤال خطر جدا
because it leads you to the path of fundamentalism and violence.
لأنه سيؤدي بنا إلى التعصب والعنف
So, I will not answer the question.
لذلك لن اجاوب على السؤال
What I will give you is an Indian answer,
ولكن ساعطيكم الإجابة الهندية
the Indian head-shake.
هزة الرأس الهندية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Depending on the context,
بناءا على المحتوى
depending on the outcome,
بناء على النتيجة
choose your paradigm.
اختار طريقك
You see, because both the paradigms are human constructions.
كما ترون، لأن الطريقين هما بناء إنساني
They are cultural creations,
خلقتهم ثقافتنا وخلفياتنا الحضارية
not natural phenomena.
ليسا ظواهر طبيعية
And so the next time you meet someone, a stranger,
ولذلك في المرة القادمة التي تقابل فيها شخصا ما، غريب
one request:
رجاء واحد
Understand that you live in the subjective truth,
تفهم أنك تعيش الحقيقة المطلقة
and so does he.
كذلك هو
Understand it.
أفهم
And when you understand it you will discover something spectacular.
وعندما تفهم ستكتشف شيئا مذهلا
You will discover that within infinite myths
ستكتشف انه بداخل الأساطير اللانهائية
lies the eternal truth.
تكمن الحقيقة الخالدة
Who sees it all?
من يرى كل شيء؟
Varuna has but a thousand eyes.
الإله "فارونا" يملك ألف عين
Indra, a hundred.
الإله "إندرا" يملك مائة
You and I, only two.
انت وانا، اثنان فقط
Thank you. Namaste.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)